<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>process tracing | Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck</title>
    <link>/category/process-tracing/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/process-tracing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>process tracing</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>process tracing</title>
      <link>/category/process-tracing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>What HoPTM looks like from the inside</title>
      <link>/post/what-hoptm-looks-like-from-the-inside/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/what-hoptm-looks-like-from-the-inside/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As mentioned some days ago our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.schulte-mecklenbeck.com/post/hoptm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Handbook of Process Tracing Methods&lt;/a&gt; is out in the wild &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a bit of an overview of what is going on inside :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book has 390 pages divided into 24 chapters. There are 202014 words in there including everything (references, thanks, hello, goodbye &amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ignoring the chapters and that they have reference lists, that mess up things a bit, first an overview of frequency for highly frequent words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/images/words_frequency.pdf&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No big surprises there for a process tracing book in decision making - but still - models pop up quite high in the list and trajectories - the new kid on the block when it comes to mousetracking also gets a mention - the list is truncated and I did not bother to remove things like &amp;lsquo;et al.&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;e.g&amp;rsquo; (the second . got caught by the script, the first one not).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/images/words_per_chapter.pdf&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is more interesting - I calculated the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tf%e2%80%93idf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tf-idf&lt;/a&gt; (term frequency–inverse document frequency) which tells us how important a word is but takes care of how often a word appears in general - so a better measure than just using the raw frequency of a word. I did this for each chapter (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.schulte-mecklenbeck.com/post/hoptm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;chapter names&lt;/a&gt; are listed in the other post). At first I wanted to remove the reference list but I realized that it provides an interesting insight - namely how often authors cite themselves in their chapters. A caveat in this graph is that the x-axis has different scaling. Apart from that it actually describes the content of some of the chapters pretty well - ah and I just saw that I should have added some stemming to avoid &amp;lsquo;clusters&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;cluster&amp;rsquo; being listed separatly &amp;hellip; but well &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the kicks - here is a network diagram of bigrams. There is clearly some more work to do here &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/images/network.pdf&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shoutout to the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidytextmining.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tidytext&lt;/a&gt; people - you got a great package there!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Handbook of Process Tracing Methods</title>
      <link>/post/hoptm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/hoptm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;WOOP WOOP - here it is - the second edition of our beloved &amp;ldquo;Handbook of Process Tracing Methods&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can&amp;rsquo;t wait - buy it here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crcpress.com/A-Handbook-of-Process-Tracing-Methods-2nd-Edition/Schulte-Mecklenbeck-Kuehberger-Johnson/p/book/9781138064218&#34;&gt;https://www.crcpress.com/A-Handbook-of-Process-Tracing-Methods-2nd-Edition/Schulte-Mecklenbeck-Kuehberger-Johnson/p/book/9781138064218&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is bigger and better than the first edition, comes with the classics (Figner on skin conductance, Willemsen on Mouselab and many more) and many new awesome chapters - here is a list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Eye Fixations as a Process Trace - J. Edward Russo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 Pervasive Eye-Tracking for Real-World Consumer Behavior Analysis - Andreas Bulling and Michel Wedel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 Investigating Pupil Dilation in Decision Research - Joseph Tao-yi Wang and Wei James Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 A Primer on Eye-Tracking Methodology for Behavioral Science - Jacob L. Orquin and Kenneth Holmqvist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 Increasing Reproducibility of Eye-Tracking Studies: The EyeGuidelines - Susann Fiedler, Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck, Frank Renkewitz, and Jacob L. Orquin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 (Re)Visiting the Decision Factory: Observing Cognition with MouselabWEB - Martijn C. Willemsen and Eric J. Johnson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 Comparing Process Tracing Paradigms: Tracking Attention via Mouse and Eye Movements - Ana M. Franco-Watkins, Hayden K. Hickey, and Joseph G. Johnson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 Mouse-Tracking: A Practical Guide to Implementation and Analysis - Pascal J. Kieslich, Felix Henninger, Dirk U. Wulff, Jonas M. B. Haslbeck, and Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9 Mouse-Tracking: Detecting Types in Movement Trajectories - Dirk U. Wulff, Jonas M. B. Haslbeck, Pascal J. Kieslich, Felix Henninger, and Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 Mouse-Tracking to Understand Real-Time Dynamics of Social Cognition - Benjamin S. Stillerman and Jonathan B. Freeman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11 Measuring Electrodermal Activity and Its Applications in Judgment and Decision-Making Research - Bernd Figner, Ryan O. Murphy, and Paul Siegel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12 Response Times as Identification Tools for Cognitive Processes Underlying Decisions - Mario Fifić, Joseph W. Houpt, and Jörg Rieskamp&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 A Practical Guide for Automated Facial Emotion Classification - Sabrina Stöckli, Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck, Stefan Borer, and Andrea C. Samson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14 EEG and ERPs as Neural Process Tracing Methodologies in Decision-Making Research - Mary E. Frame&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 Decision Neuroscience: fMRI Insights into Choice Processes - Vinod Venkatraman and Crystal Reeck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;16 Probing the Decisional Brain with Noninvasive Brain Stimulation - Nadège Bault, Elena Rusconi, and Giorgio Coricelli&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17 Verbal Reports and Decision Process Analysis - Rob Ranyard and Ola Svenson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;18 Thinking Aloud during Superior Performance on Tasks Involving Decision Making - K.Anders Ericsson and Jerad H. Moxley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 Tracking Free Information Access: The Method of Active Information Search - Oswald Huber, Anton Kühberger, and Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20 Uncovering the Anatomy of Search Without Technology - Dirk U. Wulff and Ralph Hertwig&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;21 Process Tracing, Sampling, and Drift Rate Construction - Neil Stewart and Timothy L. Mullett&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;22 Using Multiple Methods to Elicit Choices and to Identify Strategies - Ulrich Hoffrage and Nils Reisen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;23 Testing Cognitive Models by a Joint Analysis of Multiple Dependent Measures Including Process Data - Andreas Glöckner and Marc Jekel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;24 Using Process Tracing Data to Define and Test Process Models - Joseph G. Johnson and Mary E. Frame&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019-06-20-handbook-of-process-tracing-methods_files/0_Cover.tif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BernR Meetup</title>
      <link>/post/2019-06-04-hoptm2ndedition/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 06:05:56 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019-06-04-hoptm2ndedition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today (Dec 10th 2018) we will meet for the first BernR Meetup (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.meetup.com/Bern-R/&#34;&gt;https://www.meetup.com/Bern-R/&lt;/a&gt;) – hope to learn new things and get to know cool R people. More to follow soon ..&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Growing up to be old</title>
      <link>/post/2017-04-12-growing-up-to-be-old/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 07:45:12 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017-04-12-growing-up-to-be-old/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some papers have somewhat weird starting points – this one had an awesome starting point – Lake Louise (Canada):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-large wp-image-505&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2017/04/canada-1024x347.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;584&#34; height=&#34;198&#34; srcset=&#34;2017/04/canada-1024x347.jpg 1024w, 2017/04/canada-300x102.jpg 300w, 2017/04/canada-768x260.jpg 768w, 2017/04/canada-1477x500.jpg 1477w, 2017/04/canada-500x169.jpg 500w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px&#34; /&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-507&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2017/04/wprkshop.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;423&#34; height=&#34;372&#34; srcset=&#34;2017/04/wprkshop.jpg 423w, 2017/04/wprkshop-300x264.jpg 300w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 423px) 100vw, 423px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a little suite we (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://miamioh.edu/cas/academics/departments/psychology/about/current-faculty-staff/johnson-joseph/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Joe Johnson&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kellogg.northwestern.edu/faculty/directory/bockenholt_ulf.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ulf Böckenholt&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dangoldstein.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dan Goldstein&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.johnson.cornell.edu/Faculty-And-Research/Profile?id=jer9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jay Russo&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.duke.edu/huettellab/post-doc-nikki-sullivan/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nikki Sullivan&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tue.nl/en/university/departments/industrial-engineering-innovation-sciences/the-department/staff/detail/ep/e/d/ep-uid/19980508/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Martijn Willemsen&lt;/a&gt;) sat down during a conference called the ‘
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.choicesymposium.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Choice Symposium&lt;/a&gt;‘ and started working on an overview paper about the history and current status of different process tracing methods. One central result (why can’t all papers be like that) is the figure below where we try to locate many process tracing methods on the two dimensions: temporal resolution and distortion risk (i.e., how fast can a method measure a process and how destructive is this measurement).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schulte-Mecklenbeck, M., Johnson, J.G., Böckenholt, U., Goldstein, D., Russo, J., Sullivan, N., &amp;amp;  Willemsen, M. (in press). Process tracing methods in decision making: On growing up in the 70ties. &lt;em&gt;Current Directions in Psychological Science&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-503&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2017/04/40years.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;2496&#34; height=&#34;1404&#34; srcset=&#34;2017/04/40years.png 2496w, 2017/04/40years-300x169.png 300w, 2017/04/40years-768x432.png 768w, 2017/04/40years-1024x576.png 1024w, 2017/04/40years-889x500.png 889w, 2017/04/40years-500x281.png 500w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 2496px) 100vw, 2496px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah – everybody was trying to find a path all the time:&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-large wp-image-506&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2017/04/lost-1024x768.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;584&#34; height=&#34;438&#34; srcset=&#34;2017/04/lost-1024x768.jpg 1024w, 2017/04/lost-300x225.jpg 300w, 2017/04/lost-768x576.jpg 768w, 2017/04/lost-667x500.jpg 667w, 2017/04/lost-500x375.jpg 500w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Something about reverse inference</title>
      <link>/post/2017-04-12-something-about-reverse-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 07:29:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017-04-12-something-about-reverse-inference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;page&#34; title=&#34;Page 1&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;layoutArea&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;column&#34;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Often, when we run process tracing studies (e.g., eye-tracking, mouse-tracking, thinking-aloud) we talk about cognitive processes (things we can&amp;#8217;t observe) in a way that they are actually and directly observable. This is pretty weird &amp;#8211; which becomes obvious when looking at the data from the paper below. In this paper we simply instruct participants to follow a strategy when making choices between risky gamble problems. Taking the example of fixation duration we see that there is surprisingly litte difference between calculating an expected value, using a heuristic (priority heuristic) and just making decisions without instructions (no instruction) &amp;#8230; maybe we should rethink our mapping of observation to cognitive processes a bit?
      &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
    Here is the paper:
  &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
    Schulte-Mecklenbeck, M., Kühberger, A., Gagl, S., &amp;amp; Hutzler, F. (in press). Inducing thought processes: Bringing process measures and cognitive processes closer together. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Journal of Behavioral Decision Making&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. [ &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;/uploads//2009/05/Schulte-Mecklenbeck2017.pdf&amp;quot;&amp;gt;PDF&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; ]
  &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;img class=&amp;quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-499&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;/uploads//2017/04/fixduration.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;996&amp;quot; height=&amp;quot;582&amp;quot; srcset=&amp;quot;2017/04/fixduration.png 996w, 2017/04/fixduration-300x175.png 300w, 2017/04/fixduration-768x449.png 768w, 2017/04/fixduration-856x500.png 856w, 2017/04/fixduration-500x292.png 500w&amp;quot; sizes=&amp;quot;(max-width: 996px) 100vw, 996px&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;column&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
    &amp;amp;nbsp;
  &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
    Abstract:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; The challenge in inferring cognitive processes from observational data is to correctly align overt behavior with its covert cognitive process. To improve our understanding of the overt–covert mapping in the domain of decision making, we collected eye-movement data during decisions between gamble-problems. Participants were either free to choose or instructed to use a specific choice strategy (maximizing expected value or a choice heuristic). We found large differences in looking patterns between free and instructed choices. Looking patterns provided no support for the common assumption that attention is equally distributed between outcomes and probabilities, even when participants were instructed to maximize expected value. Eye-movement data are to some extent ambiguous with respect to underlying cognitive processes.
  &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
