<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>ReproducibiliTea comes to UniBe</title>
      <link>/post/2021-03-22-reproducibilitea-comes-to-unibe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2021-03-22-reproducibilitea-comes-to-unibe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Talking about reproducibility while drinking tea, well, there you go - ReproducibiliTea, fresh and new @UniBe: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://unibe-reptea.netlify.app&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://unibe-reptea.netlify.app&lt;/a&gt; &amp;hellip; every second month, one paper, researchers from UniBe - sounds awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Science Lecture Series</title>
      <link>/post/open-science-lecture-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/open-science-lecture-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This will be fun - Lecture series on Open Science, Replication, Reproducability, Open Data and many more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly interdisciplinary series with speakers from business, psychology, life science, medicine, library sciences and informatics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be there or be &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/images/OpenScience2020.pdf&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What HoPTM looks like from the inside</title>
      <link>/post/what-hoptm-looks-like-from-the-inside/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/what-hoptm-looks-like-from-the-inside/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As mentioned some days ago our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.schulte-mecklenbeck.com/post/hoptm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Handbook of Process Tracing Methods&lt;/a&gt; is out in the wild &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a bit of an overview of what is going on inside :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book has 390 pages divided into 24 chapters. There are 202014 words in there including everything (references, thanks, hello, goodbye &amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ignoring the chapters and that they have reference lists, that mess up things a bit, first an overview of frequency for highly frequent words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/images/words_frequency.pdf&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No big surprises there for a process tracing book in decision making - but still - models pop up quite high in the list and trajectories - the new kid on the block when it comes to mousetracking also gets a mention - the list is truncated and I did not bother to remove things like &amp;rsquo;et al.&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo;e.g&amp;rsquo; (the second . got caught by the script, the first one not).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/images/words_per_chapter.pdf&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is more interesting - I calculated the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tf%e2%80%93idf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tf-idf&lt;/a&gt; (term frequency–inverse document frequency) which tells us how important a word is but takes care of how often a word appears in general - so a better measure than just using the raw frequency of a word. I did this for each chapter (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.schulte-mecklenbeck.com/post/hoptm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;chapter names&lt;/a&gt; are listed in the other post). At first I wanted to remove the reference list but I realized that it provides an interesting insight - namely how often authors cite themselves in their chapters. A caveat in this graph is that the x-axis has different scaling. Apart from that it actually describes the content of some of the chapters pretty well - ah and I just saw that I should have added some stemming to avoid &amp;lsquo;clusters&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;cluster&amp;rsquo; being listed separatly &amp;hellip; but well &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the kicks - here is a network diagram of bigrams. There is clearly some more work to do here &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/images/network.pdf&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shoutout to the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidytextmining.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tidytext&lt;/a&gt; people - you got a great package there!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Handbook of Process Tracing Methods</title>
      <link>/post/hoptm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/hoptm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;WOOP WOOP - here it is - the second edition of our beloved &amp;ldquo;Handbook of Process Tracing Methods&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can&amp;rsquo;t wait - buy it here: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crcpress.com/A-Handbook-of-Process-Tracing-Methods-2nd-Edition/Schulte-Mecklenbeck-Kuehberger-Johnson/p/book/9781138064218&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.crcpress.com/A-Handbook-of-Process-Tracing-Methods-2nd-Edition/Schulte-Mecklenbeck-Kuehberger-Johnson/p/book/9781138064218&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is bigger and better than the first edition, comes with the classics (Figner on skin conductance, Willemsen on Mouselab and many more) and many new awesome chapters - here is a list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Eye Fixations as a Process Trace - J. Edward Russo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 Pervasive Eye-Tracking for Real-World Consumer Behavior Analysis - Andreas Bulling and Michel Wedel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 Investigating Pupil Dilation in Decision Research - Joseph Tao-yi Wang and Wei James Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 A Primer on Eye-Tracking Methodology for Behavioral Science - Jacob L. Orquin and Kenneth Holmqvist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 Increasing Reproducibility of Eye-Tracking Studies: The EyeGuidelines - Susann Fiedler, Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck, Frank Renkewitz, and Jacob L. Orquin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 (Re)Visiting the Decision Factory: Observing Cognition with MouselabWEB - Martijn C. Willemsen and Eric J. Johnson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 Comparing Process Tracing Paradigms: Tracking Attention via Mouse and Eye Movements - Ana M. Franco-Watkins, Hayden K. Hickey, and Joseph G. Johnson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 Mouse-Tracking: A Practical Guide to Implementation and Analysis - Pascal J. Kieslich, Felix Henninger, Dirk U. Wulff, Jonas M. B. Haslbeck, and Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9 Mouse-Tracking: Detecting Types in Movement Trajectories - Dirk U. Wulff, Jonas M. B. Haslbeck, Pascal J. Kieslich, Felix Henninger, and Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 Mouse-Tracking to Understand Real-Time Dynamics of Social Cognition - Benjamin S. Stillerman and Jonathan B. Freeman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11 Measuring Electrodermal Activity and Its Applications in Judgment and Decision-Making Research - Bernd Figner, Ryan O. Murphy, and Paul Siegel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12 Response Times as Identification Tools for Cognitive Processes Underlying Decisions - Mario Fifić, Joseph W. Houpt, and Jörg Rieskamp&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 A Practical Guide for Automated Facial Emotion Classification - Sabrina Stöckli, Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck, Stefan Borer, and Andrea C. Samson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14 EEG and ERPs as Neural Process Tracing Methodologies in Decision-Making Research - Mary E. Frame&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 Decision Neuroscience: fMRI Insights into Choice Processes - Vinod Venkatraman and Crystal Reeck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;16 Probing the Decisional Brain with Noninvasive Brain Stimulation - Nadège Bault, Elena Rusconi, and Giorgio Coricelli&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17 Verbal Reports and Decision Process Analysis - Rob Ranyard and Ola Svenson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;18 Thinking Aloud during Superior Performance on Tasks Involving Decision Making - K.Anders Ericsson and Jerad H. Moxley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 Tracking Free Information Access: The Method of Active Information Search - Oswald Huber, Anton Kühberger, and Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20 Uncovering the Anatomy of Search Without Technology - Dirk U. Wulff and Ralph Hertwig&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;21 Process Tracing, Sampling, and Drift Rate Construction - Neil Stewart and Timothy L. Mullett&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;22 Using Multiple Methods to Elicit Choices and to Identify Strategies - Ulrich Hoffrage and Nils Reisen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;23 Testing Cognitive Models by a Joint Analysis of Multiple Dependent Measures Including Process Data - Andreas Glöckner and Marc Jekel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;24 Using Process Tracing Data to Define and Test Process Models - Joseph G. Johnson and Mary E. Frame&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019-06-20-handbook-of-process-tracing-methods_files/0_Cover.tif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pictures</title>
      <link>/post/pictures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/pictures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, here we go - new blogdown site &amp;hellip; thanks to Dan (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dsquintana&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/dsquintana&lt;/a&gt;) to kicked me over the edge actually doing this &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things are fine, the site is up - pictures are still linked back to my old wordpress site &amp;hellip; will figure this out eventually &amp;hellip; but this is live now - for your reading pleasure :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BernR Meetup</title>
      <link>/post/2019-06-04-hoptm2ndedition/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 06:05:56 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019-06-04-hoptm2ndedition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today (Dec 10th 2018) we will meet for the first BernR Meetup (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.meetup.com/Bern-R/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.meetup.com/Bern-R/&lt;/a&gt;) – hope to learn new things and get to know cool R people. More to follow soon ..&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BernR Meetup</title>
      <link>/post/2018-12-10-bernr-meetup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2018 06:05:56 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2018-12-10-bernr-meetup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today (Dec 10th 2018) we will meet for the first BernR Meetup (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.meetup.com/Bern-R/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.meetup.com/Bern-R/&lt;/a&gt;) – hope to learn new things and get to know cool R people. More to follow soon ..&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A letter to the black goat</title>
      <link>/post/2018-07-30-a-letter-to-the-black-goat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 21:16:40 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2018-07-30-a-letter-to-the-black-goat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I wrote this letter to 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theblackgoatpodcast.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the black goat&lt;/a&gt; podcast … will update here if I hear back from them …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear goaters (is this a good way to address the three of you?),&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  I attended SIPS some weeks ago (first timer). I was unsure what to expect but got a lot of bang for my buck (which is great) &amp;#8211; as a side note I would recommend first timers to try to go there with a concrete project or question or problem, I think there is a good chance to find people with similar issues interested in collaborations.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  Here is an observation I would be interested to hear your thoughts on: in the SIPS world everything seems to be really straight forward &amp;#8211; we want to &amp;#8216;unfuck psych science&amp;#8217; (Lindsay, 2018), we want to pre-reg studies, upload data, learn R, comment on code, accelerate science, ‘do it right this time’, collaborate, respect, be inclusive (I really learned a lot in that regard listening to your podcast and talking to people at SIPS) …
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  All of that is great. I subscribe to all of these points.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  Here is the twist &amp;#8211; people @SIPS talk about &amp;#8216;a movement’  (something that seems very American to me), maybe a movement is needed; people @SIPS talk about ‘a revolution’ &amp;#8211; again, great! obviously there is a need to rattle the cage and accelerate things beyond ‘paradigm shifts at funerals’ (Planck?)
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  BUT
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  What happens if you go ‘Outside the SIPS Bubble&amp;#8217; (OSIPSB)?
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  I have no data (other than my own experiences) but I wonder whether the world (psychology, other sciences) is actually that ready, that willing and open to adopt to these new standards and to actually make a paradigm shift in how we do science. I work at a business school (consumer psych and JDM) there is a lot of finger pointing going on toward psychology (I have a similar feeling that within psychology there is a lot of finger pointing toward social psych) &amp;#8211; &amp;#8216;this is clearly a problem of psychologists but not of us [economists, consumer psychologists, business, accounting researchers &amp;#8230;]’.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  Another OSIPSB experience I had was talking to an Action Editor of the Journal of Consumer Psychology (JCR) last year &amp;#8211; we got into a heated debate about the most basic issues, eg, sharing data, pre-reg studies …
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  Is this an observation you share? What would be good steps to address these issues? Should we talk about this within SIPS to get a better balance between enthusiasm and real world requirements (eg hiring decisions are still made mostly by senior faculty, assuming my observation hold, less interested in replication than ’new and exciting effects’ (quote anonymous senior AE of JCR).
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  Thanks for your thoughts!
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPDATE in 2019 - on my way to SIPS2019, casually started listening to some podcasts - and then this: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.podbean.com/ew/pb-2iqpx-b6aa1e&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.podbean.com/ew/pb-2iqpx-b6aa1e&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blind Haste (aka im Blindflug)</title>
      <link>/post/2018-01-09-blind-haste-aka-im-blindflug/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2018 05:47:29 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2018-01-09-blind-haste-aka-im-blindflug/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chance encounters sometimes lead to interesting and new projects. This is one of those cases … I got to know 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.alexandria.unisg.ch/persons/4948&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Emanuel de Bellis&lt;/a&gt; during my time at Nestle and we never stopped collaborating ever since (he actually lead my 2017 ‘skype to’ statistics with my wife as a close second …)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got our hands on a rich dataset of speed measures the police in Zürich (Switzerland) does unbeknownst to the drivers during they year for planning purposes. The radar is put into a small black box hardly anybody realises driving by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter wp-image-604&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2018/01/IMG_2465.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;74&#34; height=&#34;252&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;(it’s the black box above the bin – not the bin!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So – we got these data from over a million cars and got to work with them trying to find an answer to a question in perception research: Do people perceive their environment differently when light conditions deteriorate? and (even more important) Do drivers change their driving speed accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well – they don’t … and here is correlational proof 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for a causal demonstration – oh yes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;artTitle&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0188951&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Blind haste: As light decreases, speeding increases&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worldwide, more than one million people die on the roads each year. A third of these fatal accidents are attributed to speeding, with properties of the individual driver and the environment regarded as key contributing factors. We examine real-world speeding behavior and its interaction with illuminance, an environmental property defined as the luminous flux incident on a surface. Drawing on an analysis of 1.2 million vehicle movements, we show that reduced illuminance levels are associated with increased speeding. This relationship persists when we control for factors known to influence speeding (e.g., fluctuations in traffic volume) and consider proxies of illuminance (e.g., sight distance). Our findings add to a long-standing debate about how the quality of visual conditions affects drivers’ speed perception and driving speed. Policy makers can intervene by educating drivers about the inverse illuminance‒speeding relationship and by testing how improved vehicle headlights and smart road lighting can attenuate speeding.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professor priming - or not</title>
      <link>/post/2017-11-13-professor-priming-or-not/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 14:23:40 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017-11-13-professor-priming-or-not/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;page&#34; title=&#34;Page 2&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;section&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;layoutArea&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;column&#34;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
          This was my first contribution to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologicalscience.org/publications/replication-dijksterhuis-van-knippenberg&#34;&gt;Registered Replication Report&lt;/a&gt; (RRR). Being one of 40 participating labs was an interesting exercise &amp;#8211; it might seem straightforward to run the same study in different labs, but we learned that such small things as ü, ä and ö can generate a huge amount of problems and work (read &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTF-8&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; if you are into these kind of things).
        &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
      Here is one of the central results:
    &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
    
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;img class=&amp;quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-579&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;/uploads//2017/11/Screen-Shot-2017-11-13-at-22.19.39.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;718&amp;quot; height=&amp;quot;609&amp;quot; srcset=&amp;quot;2017/11/Screen-Shot-2017-11-13-at-22.19.39.png 718w, 2017/11/Screen-Shot-2017-11-13-at-22.19.39-300x254.png 300w, 2017/11/Screen-Shot-2017-11-13-at-22.19.39-589x500.png 589w, 2017/11/Screen-Shot-2017-11-13-at-22.19.39-500x424.png 500w&amp;quot; sizes=&amp;quot;(max-width: 718px) 100vw, 718px&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
    
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
      So overall not a lot of action &amp;amp;#8230; our lab was actually the one with larges effect size (in the predicted direction).
    &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
    
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
      Here is the abstract of the whole paper and here the &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://www.psychologicalscience.org/redesign/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/Dijksterhuis_RRRcommentary_ACPT.pdf&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Commentary by Ap Dijksterhuis&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; naturally, he sees things a bit different:           Dijksterhuis and van Knippenberg (1998) reported that participants primed with an intelligent category (“professor”) subsequently performed 13.1% better on a trivia test than participants primed with an unintelligent category (“soccer hooligans”). Two unpublished replications of this study by the original authors, designed to verify the appropriate testing procedures, observed a smaller difference between conditions (2-3%) as well as a gender difference: men showed the effect (9.3% and 7.6%) but women did not (0.3% and -0.3%). The procedure used in those replications served as the basis for this multi-lab Registered Replication Report (RRR). A total of 40 laboratories collected data for this project, with 23 laboratories meeting all inclusion criteria. Here we report the meta-analytic result of those 23 direct replications (total N = 4,493) of the updated version of the original study, examining the difference between priming with professor and hooligan on a 30-item general knowledge trivia task (a supplementary analysis reports results with all 40 labs, N = 6,454). We observed no overall difference in trivia performance between participants primed with professor and those primed with hooligan (0.14%) and no moderation by gender.
    &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The root of the problem</title>
      <link>/post/2017-11-13-the-root-of-the-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 05:44:06 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017-11-13-the-root-of-the-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the root causes of where we are (as a science) in psychology and many other disciplines in terms of reproducibility of key (and other) results could not be better summed up than by the man himself Daryl Bem (2002):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If a datum suggests a new hypothesis, try to find additional evidence for it elsewhere in the data. If you see dim traces of interesting patterns, try to reorganize the data to bring them into bolder relief. If there are participants you don’t like, or trials, observers, or interviewers who gave you anomalous results, drop them (temporarily). Go on a fishing expedition for something — anything — interesting. ”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Go on a fishing expidition’ – why should there come anything good from such advise? Bem goes on …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No, this is not immoral (SIC!). The rules of scientific and statistical inference that we overlearn in graduate school apply to the “Context of Justification.” They tell us what we can conclude in the articles we write for public consumption, and they give our readers criteria for deciding whether or not to believe us. But in the “Context of Discovery,” there are no formal rules, only heuristics or strategies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I disagree with this statement, because the idea of finding something through torturing the data (until they confess) is a hug source of false positive results. We find an effect and falsely conclude that something is there when in fact there is nothing. I found the above quote when reading 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/4tg9c/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; by Zwaan, Etz, Lucas &amp;amp; Donnellan (2017) – a target article for 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/behavioral-and-brain-sciences&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BBS&lt;/a&gt; which presents six common arguments against replication and a set of really good responses for such discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the six ‘concerns’ the authors discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;page&#34; title=&#34;Page 14&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;section&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;layoutArea&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;column&#34;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
          Concern I: Context Is Too Variable&lt;br /&gt; Concern II: The Theoretical Value of Direct Replications is Limited&lt;br /&gt; Concern III: Direct Replications Are Not Feasible in Certain Domains&lt;br /&gt; Concern IV: Replications are a Distraction&lt;br /&gt; Concern V: Replications Affect Reputations&lt;br /&gt; Concern VI: There is no Standard Method to Evaluate Replication Results
        &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
      Both are really good reads &amp;amp;#8211; for very different reasons.
    &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
    
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
      &amp;amp;nbsp;
    &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
    
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
      &amp;amp;#8212;
    &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bern, D. (2002). Writing the empirical journal article. In Darley, J. M., Zanna, M. P., &amp;amp; Roediger III, H. L. (Eds) (2002). &lt;em&gt;The Compleat Academic: A Career Guide&lt;/em&gt;. Washington, DC: American Psychological Association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zwaan, R. A., Etz, A., Lucas, R. E., &amp;amp; Donnellan, B. (2017, November 1). Making Replication Mainstream. Retrieved from 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/4tg9c&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;psyarxiv.com/4tg9c&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A short history of process tracing</title>
      <link>/post/2017-10-31-a-short-history-of-process-tracing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 00:10:34 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017-10-31-a-short-history-of-process-tracing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally out (already mentioned 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.schulte-mecklenbeck.com/2017/04/growing-up-to-be-old/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;earlier this year&lt;/a&gt;) – now in it’s full glory @ 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/pdf/10.1177/0963721417708229&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Current Directions in Psychological Science.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good Stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-width=&#34;550&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
    a little process tracing history together with the delightful &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dggoldst?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@dggoldst&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/svGBLYcAZv&#34;&gt;https://t.co/svGBLYcAZv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/processtracing?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#processtracing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JDM?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JDM&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;mdash; Michael Schulte (@SchulteMi) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SchulteMi/status/925243864671285248?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 31, 2017&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LaTeX &lt;- pdfTeX, LuaTeX, XeTeX</title>
      <link>/post/2017-04-30-latex/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 23:16:22 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017-04-30-latex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been using LaTeX (with pdfTeX) for 20+ years now – to be honest I never bothered to understand the differences between the different TeX engines – 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com/blog/500-whats-in-a-name-a-guide-to-the-many-flavours-of-tex#.WQbPt1KB3UI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is an excellent article by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/publishergeek&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Graham Douglas&lt;/a&gt; explaining the ins and outs of the TeX engine(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… the article also features 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt; a shared TeX environment … sweet!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Growing up to be old</title>
      <link>/post/2017-04-12-growing-up-to-be-old/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 07:45:12 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017-04-12-growing-up-to-be-old/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some papers have somewhat weird starting points – this one had an awesome starting point – Lake Louise (Canada):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-large wp-image-505&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2017/04/canada-1024x347.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;584&#34; height=&#34;198&#34; srcset=&#34;2017/04/canada-1024x347.jpg 1024w, 2017/04/canada-300x102.jpg 300w, 2017/04/canada-768x260.jpg 768w, 2017/04/canada-1477x500.jpg 1477w, 2017/04/canada-500x169.jpg 500w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px&#34; /&gt;  
&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-507&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2017/04/wprkshop.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;423&#34; height=&#34;372&#34; srcset=&#34;2017/04/wprkshop.jpg 423w, 2017/04/wprkshop-300x264.jpg 300w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 423px) 100vw, 423px&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;In a little suite we (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://miamioh.edu/cas/academics/departments/psychology/about/current-faculty-staff/johnson-joseph/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Joe Johnson&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kellogg.northwestern.edu/faculty/directory/bockenholt_ulf.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ulf Böckenholt&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dangoldstein.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dan Goldstein&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.johnson.cornell.edu/Faculty-And-Research/Profile?id=jer9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jay Russo&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.duke.edu/huettellab/post-doc-nikki-sullivan/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nikki Sullivan&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tue.nl/en/university/departments/industrial-engineering-innovation-sciences/the-department/staff/detail/ep/e/d/ep-uid/19980508/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Martijn Willemsen&lt;/a&gt;) sat down during a conference called the ‘
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.choicesymposium.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Choice Symposium&lt;/a&gt;‘ and started working on an overview paper about the history and current status of different process tracing methods. One central result (why can’t all papers be like that) is the figure below where we try to locate many process tracing methods on the two dimensions: temporal resolution and distortion risk (i.e., how fast can a method measure a process and how destructive is this measurement).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schulte-Mecklenbeck, M., Johnson, J.G., Böckenholt, U., Goldstein, D., Russo, J., Sullivan, N., &amp;amp;  Willemsen, M. (in press). Process tracing methods in decision making: On growing up in the 70ties. &lt;em&gt;Current Directions in Psychological Science&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-503&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2017/04/40years.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;2496&#34; height=&#34;1404&#34; srcset=&#34;2017/04/40years.png 2496w, 2017/04/40years-300x169.png 300w, 2017/04/40years-768x432.png 768w, 2017/04/40years-1024x576.png 1024w, 2017/04/40years-889x500.png 889w, 2017/04/40years-500x281.png 500w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 2496px) 100vw, 2496px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah – everybody was trying to find a path all the time:&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-large wp-image-506&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2017/04/lost-1024x768.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;584&#34; height=&#34;438&#34; srcset=&#34;2017/04/lost-1024x768.jpg 1024w, 2017/04/lost-300x225.jpg 300w, 2017/04/lost-768x576.jpg 768w, 2017/04/lost-667x500.jpg 667w, 2017/04/lost-500x375.jpg 500w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Something about reverse inference</title>
      <link>/post/2017-04-12-something-about-reverse-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 07:29:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017-04-12-something-about-reverse-inference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;page&#34; title=&#34;Page 1&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;layoutArea&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;column&#34;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Often, when we run process tracing studies (e.g., eye-tracking, mouse-tracking, thinking-aloud) we talk about cognitive processes (things we can&amp;#8217;t observe) in a way that they are actually and directly observable. This is pretty weird &amp;#8211; which becomes obvious when looking at the data from the paper below. In this paper we simply instruct participants to follow a strategy when making choices between risky gamble problems. Taking the example of fixation duration we see that there is surprisingly litte difference between calculating an expected value, using a heuristic (priority heuristic) and just making decisions without instructions (no instruction) &amp;#8230; maybe we should rethink our mapping of observation to cognitive processes a bit?
      &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
    Here is the paper:
  &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
    Schulte-Mecklenbeck, M., Kühberger, A., Gagl, S., &amp;amp; Hutzler, F. (in press). Inducing thought processes: Bringing process measures and cognitive processes closer together. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Journal of Behavioral Decision Making&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. [ &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;/uploads//2009/05/Schulte-Mecklenbeck2017.pdf&amp;quot;&amp;gt;PDF&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; ]
  &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;img class=&amp;quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-499&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;/uploads//2017/04/fixduration.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;996&amp;quot; height=&amp;quot;582&amp;quot; srcset=&amp;quot;2017/04/fixduration.png 996w, 2017/04/fixduration-300x175.png 300w, 2017/04/fixduration-768x449.png 768w, 2017/04/fixduration-856x500.png 856w, 2017/04/fixduration-500x292.png 500w&amp;quot; sizes=&amp;quot;(max-width: 996px) 100vw, 996px&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;column&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
    &amp;amp;nbsp;
  &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
    Abstract:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; The challenge in inferring cognitive processes from observational data is to correctly align overt behavior with its covert cognitive process. To improve our understanding of the overt–covert mapping in the domain of decision making, we collected eye-movement data during decisions between gamble-problems. Participants were either free to choose or instructed to use a specific choice strategy (maximizing expected value or a choice heuristic). We found large differences in looking patterns between free and instructed choices. Looking patterns provided no support for the common assumption that attention is equally distributed between outcomes and probabilities, even when participants were instructed to maximize expected value. Eye-movement data are to some extent ambiguous with respect to underlying cognitive processes.
  &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eye-Tracking with N &gt; 1</title>
      <link>/post/2017-03-13-eye-tracking-with-n-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 12:20:52 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017-03-13-eye-tracking-with-n-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is one of the fastest papers I have ever written. It was a great collaboration with 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uib.eu/personal/ABjI1MDg3Mw/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tomás Lejarraga&lt;/a&gt; from the Universitat de les Illes Balears. Why was it great? Because it is one of the rare cases (at least in my academic life) where all people involved in a project contribute equally and quickly. Often, the weight of a contribution lies with one person which slows down things – with Tomás this was different – we were often sitting in front of a computer writing together (have never done this before, thought it would not work). Surprisingly this collaborative writing worked out very well and we had the skeleton of the paper within an afternoon. This was followed by many hours of tuning and tacking turns – but in principle we wrote the most important parts together – which was pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even cooler – you can do eye-tracking in groups, using our code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the [
&lt;a href=&#34;/uploads//2009/05/Lejarraga2016.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;] and abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recent introduction of inexpensive eye-trackers has opened up a wealth of opportunities for researchers to study attention in interactive tasks. No software package was previously available to help researchers exploit those opportunities. We created “the pyeTribe”, a software package that offers, among others, the following features: First, a communication platform between many eye-trackers to allow simultaneous recording of multiple participants. Second, the simultaneous calibration of multiple eye-trackers without the experimenter’s supervision. Third, data collection restricted to periods of interest, thus reducing the volume of data and easing analysis. We used a standard economic game (the public goods game) to examine data quality and demonstrate the potential of our software package. Moreover, we conducted a modeling analysis, which illustrates how combining process and behavioral data can improve models of human decision making behavior in social situations. Our software is open source and can thus be used and improved by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Everything you believe in is wrong &amp;#8211; or is it simply terrorism?</title>
      <link>/post/2016-09-20-everything-you-believe-in-is-wrong-or-is-it-simply-terrorism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 00:15:15 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2016-09-20-everything-you-believe-in-is-wrong-or-is-it-simply-terrorism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Replication_crisis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;replication crisis&lt;/a&gt; has many interesting effects on how people (and scientists) think about Psychology (and, of course, other fields) … Here is a nice summary of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://digest.bps.org.uk/2016/09/16/ten-famous-psychology-findings-that-its-been-difficult-to-replicate/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;effects that are hard to replicate&lt;/a&gt;. Among them ‘classics’ like the power pose or the big brother eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot is happening because of these new insights in terms of research (e.g., replication studies) and communication (e.g., 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fritz_Strack&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fritz Strack&lt;/a&gt; on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/groups/psychmap/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then this: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Susan_Fiske&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Susan Fiske&lt;/a&gt; in an 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=311301635895040&amp;amp;set=pcb.309090142801248&amp;amp;type=3&amp;amp;theater&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;upcoming piece&lt;/a&gt; in the APS Observer … I am really struggling with this rhetoric – 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://daniellakens.blogspot.ch/2016/09/why-scientific-criticism-sometimes.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Daniel Lakens to the rescue&lt;/a&gt; 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah – and of course 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://andrewgelman.com/2016/09/20/methodological-terrorism/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gelman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strava</title>
      <link>/post/2016-08-30-strava/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:25:21 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2016-08-30-strava/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Everything is fucked &amp;#8230;</title>
      <link>/post/2016-08-12-everything-is-fucked/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2016 00:05:23 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2016-08-12-everything-is-fucked/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This syllabus of an (obviously) awesome class has a ton of good reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hardsci.wordpress.com/2016/08/11/everything-is-fucked-the-syllabus/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Everything is fucked: The syllabus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Sanjay Srivastava&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would have two additions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://webcom.upmf-grenoble.fr/LIP/DMuller/resources/documents/HCAetal-IP-PPS.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A multi lab replication project on ego-depletion&lt;/a&gt; (Hagger &amp;amp; Chatzisarantis, 2016)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the [response](doi: 10.1177/1745691616652878) from Roy Baumeister and Kathleen D. Vohs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a really good statement of how f… up things are (in addition to all the other good examples above) …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p1&#34;&gt;
  “A new scientific truth does not triumph by convincing its opponents and making them see the light, but rather because its opponents eventually die, and a new generation grows up that is familiar with it.” &amp;#8211; Max Planck
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Before R there was S</title>
      <link>/post/2016-07-12-before-r-was-r-there-was-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 02:09:41 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2016-07-12-before-r-was-r-there-was-s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;p1&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;Before there was &lt;a href=&#34;https://mran.microsoft.com/documents/what-is-r/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, there was &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S_(programming_language)&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;S&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. R was modeled on a language developed at AT&amp;T Bell Labs starting in 1976 by Rick Becker and John Chambers (and, later, Alan Wilks) along with Doug Dunn, Jean McRae, and Judy Schilling.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p1&#34;&gt;
  Here is a talk by Rick Becker telling the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sec.ch9.ms/ch9/13f4/867fb951-cab9-42d1-b496-9f49a47f13f4/D1McCAWS1Baker_mid.mp4&#34;&gt;story of R&lt;/a&gt;. Good Stuff!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The exams package</title>
      <link>/post/2016-06-11-the-exams-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2016 02:09:52 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2016-06-11-the-exams-package/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I gave the R package 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/exams/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;exams&lt;/a&gt; a shot for my decision making lecture. Here is what it does:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Automatic generation of exams based on exercises in Sweave (R/LaTeX) or R/Markdown format, including multiple-choice questions and arithmetic problems. Exams can be produced in various formats, including PDF, HTML, Moodle XML, QTI 1.2 (for OLAT/OpenOLAT), QTI 2.1, ARSnova, and TCExam. In addition to fully customizable PDF exams, a standardized PDF format is provided that can be printed, scanned, and automatically evaluated.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some fiddling and help from one of the authors (the incredible nice 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uibk.ac.at/statistics/personal/zeileis/index.html.en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Achim Zeileis&lt;/a&gt;, Uni Innsbruck)  I got the following setup going:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pool of ~ 100 questions in .Rmd format (all multiple choice, 3-6 answer options) grouped into lectures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sampling out of the pool (e.g., 5 questions out of each lecture)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;random order of questions in each version of the exam (while keeping the lecture order, which I think is useful to give student more structure to work from)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;random order of the answers for each question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exam with the correct answers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-444&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2016/06/Screen-Shot-2016-06-11-at-11.00.22-203x300.png&#34; alt=&#34;Screen Shot 2016-06-11 at 11.00.22&#34; width=&#34;203&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; srcset=&#34;2016/06/Screen-Shot-2016-06-11-at-11.00.22-203x300.png 203w, 2016/06/Screen-Shot-2016-06-11-at-11.00.22-338x500.png 338w, 2016/06/Screen-Shot-2016-06-11-at-11.00.22.png 386w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 203px) 100vw, 203px&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;questions[] defining the answers to a question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;solutions[] defining the correct answers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in LaTeX the actual question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this information goes into an .Rmd file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once this is done one has to define the questions to be included (the pool) and set the details for the selection process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;sol &amp;lt;- exams2pdf(myexam, 
n = 2, 
nsamp = 5, 
dir = odir, 
 template = c(&#34;my_exam&#34;, &#34;solution&#34;), 
 encoding = &#39;UTF-8&#39;,
 header = list(Date = &#34;10.06.2016&#34;)
)&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This code would give me 2 exams with a sample of 5 questions out of each block of questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty awesome (after some setup work).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks Achim et al. !!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sublime autocompletion</title>
      <link>/post/2016-01-28-sublime-autocompletion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 08:47:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2016-01-28-sublime-autocompletion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;They say about 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sublimetext.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sublime&lt;/a&gt;: “The text editor you will fall in love with”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hmm – kind of did that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One reason being that when coding LaTeX in Sublime there is an awesome autocompletion feature:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Type ‘enum’ and you get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-431&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-28-at-16.45.37-300x104.png&#34; alt=&#34;Screen Shot 2016-01-28 at 16.45.37&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;104&#34; srcset=&#34;2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-28-at-16.45.37-300x104.png 300w, 2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-28-at-16.45.37-500x173.png 500w, 2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-28-at-16.45.37.png 730w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shift + Enter within an itemize adds a new \item&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-432&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-28-at-16.45.46-300x99.png&#34; alt=&#34;Screen Shot 2016-01-28 at 16.45.46&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;99&#34; srcset=&#34;2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-28-at-16.45.46-300x99.png 300w, 2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-28-at-16.45.46-500x165.png 500w, 2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-28-at-16.45.46.png 716w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AFK to cry … tears of joy 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://tex.stackexchange.com/questions/222845/how-to-use-the-autocompletion-of-enumerate-in-latexing-sublime-text&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Everything stolen from here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three weeks without email</title>
      <link>/post/2016-01-10-three-weeks-without-email/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2016 04:34:43 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2016-01-10-three-weeks-without-email/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time writing and answering email. Email is, according to 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://timingapp.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;timing&lt;/a&gt;, the third longest activity on my computer (although I am using three computers and can check this only on one of them – #timing please let us link computers for an overall analysis) … anyway – back to no email – as a holiday treat I decided to shut down all my email accounts 5 days before Dec. 24th and promised myself not to touch them until Jan. 11th. It turns out that I will come short one day of this plan. Nevertheless, I am quite happy with the result and the positive effects of this email absence. Needless to say that reading emails during vacation brings you back into a working mood (or never lets you out of it), not reading email had positive side effects before (I did this twice in the last 20 years of ‘doing’ emails). Many issues that come during such a break often solve themselves without intervention or can be solved quickly within a few hours after being back in the email world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I will turn on my email accounts now and see how much work has piled up … BRB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, 380 emails later – a paper submitted by a co-author, a rejection for a previous submission, a talk accepted, a chapter revised by a co-author – the best part of all this is that dealing with a ton of mails is a very quick thing, with a relatively low threshold for simply deleting out of date emails or replying quickly to urgent matters. What’s left are some longer replies I will do now …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Paper on pychodiagnosis and eye-tracking</title>
      <link>/post/2015-11-10-new-paper-on-pychodiagnosis-and-eye-tracking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 03:39:33 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2015-11-10-new-paper-on-pychodiagnosis-and-eye-tracking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cilia Witteman and Nanon Spaanjaars (my dutch connection) worked together on a piece on whether psychodiagnosticians improve over time (they don’t) in their ability to classify symptoms to DSM categories. This turned out to be a pretty cool paper combining eye-tracking data with a practical, and hopefully, relevant question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schulte-Mecklenbeck, M., Spaanjaars, N.L., &amp;amp; Witteman, C.L.M. (in press). 
&lt;a href=&#34;/uploads//2009/05/Schulte-Mecklenbeck_et_al2015.pdf&#34;&gt;The (in)visibility of psychodiagnosticians’ expertise&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Behavioral Decision Making&lt;/em&gt;. http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/bdm.1925&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;page&#34; title=&#34;Page 1&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;layoutArea&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;column&#34;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
    This study investigates decision making in mental health care. Specifically, it compares the diagnostic decision outcomes (i.e., the quality of diagnoses) and the diagnostic decision process (i.e., pre-decisional information acquisition patterns) of novice and experienced clinical psychologists. Participants’ eye movements were recorded while they completed diagnostic tasks, classifying mental disorders. In line with previous research, our findings indicate that diagnosticians’ performance is not related to their clinical experience. Eye-tracking data pro- vide corroborative evidence for this result from the process perspective: experience does not predict changes in cue inspection patterns. For future research into expertise in this domain, it is advisable to track individual differences between clinicians rather than study differences on the group level.
  &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the way I am seen, by people who know (and like) me</title>
      <link>/post/2015-07-13-the-way-i-am-seen-by-people-who-know-and-like-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2015 01:17:07 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2015-07-13-the-way-i-am-seen-by-people-who-know-and-like-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/uploads//2015/07/Michael-word-cloud.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-406&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2015/07/Michael-word-cloud-300x190.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Wordcloud&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;190&#34; srcset=&#34;2015/07/Michael-word-cloud-300x190.jpeg 300w, 2015/07/Michael-word-cloud-500x317.jpeg 500w, 2015/07/Michael-word-cloud.jpeg 640w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>about illusions</title>
      <link>/post/2015-03-11-about-illusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:58:52 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2015-03-11-about-illusions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://andrewgelman.com/2015/03/10/the-illusion-of-the-illusion-of-control/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Andrew Gelman talked&lt;/a&gt; about a really 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.schulte-mecklenbeck.com/pubs/Kuehberger1995.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;old paper&lt;/a&gt; I did together with 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uni-salzburg.at/index.php?id=29678&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Anton Kühberger&lt;/a&gt; ages ago. It was actually the first paper / ‘real’ scientific project I was involved in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It generated quite the buzz over its 20 year lifespan and was cited a whopping 13 times (stats look good without y-axis) …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/uploads//2015/03/Screen-Shot-2015-03-11-at-08.55.15.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-395&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2015/03/Screen-Shot-2015-03-11-at-08.55.15-300x93.png&#34; alt=&#34;Stats&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;93&#34; srcset=&#34;2015/03/Screen-Shot-2015-03-11-at-08.55.15-300x93.png 300w, 2015/03/Screen-Shot-2015-03-11-at-08.55.15.png 378w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to it, I was happy to see that we already talked about replication (and were very reluctant to push the button harder – as we would have not been able to get through the reviews, I guess) … Things have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schnitz(e)ljagd</title>
      <link>/post/2015-02-20-schnitzeljagd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2015 06:35:25 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2015-02-20-schnitzeljagd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.de/maps/@54.4616678,19.4255899,5z/data=!4m2!6m1!1szTqNmXl-WpAY.k4YAxe992B7I&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Find the Schnitz(e)l&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>all that mutate() and summarise() beauty</title>
      <link>/post/2015-02-12-all-that-mutate-and-summarise-beauty/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2015 01:44:10 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2015-02-12-all-that-mutate-and-summarise-beauty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The friendly people from RStudio recently started a 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rstudio.com/resources/webinars/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;webinar series&lt;/a&gt; with talks on the following topics (among others):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data wrangling with R and RStudio&lt;br&gt;
The Grammar and Graphics of Data Science (both dplyr happiness)&lt;br&gt;
RStudio and Shiny&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… and many more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our friend 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://nathanieldphillips.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Nathaniel D. Philipps&lt;/a&gt; also started a cool 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://nathanieldphillips.com/r-course/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R course&lt;/a&gt; with videos, shiny apps and many other new goodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving an idea into business</title>
      <link>/post/2015-02-07-moving-an-idea-into-business/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2015 15:15:17 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2015-02-07-moving-an-idea-into-business/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://vlab.ethz.ch/ROM/DBGT/Homepage.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ryan Murphy&lt;/a&gt; and myself realised that a startup here in Berlin features ideas of our 2011 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.schulte-mecklenbeck.com/pubs/Schulte2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Flashlight paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the guys at 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.attensee.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;attensee.com&lt;/a&gt; did a great job taking the idea we had much further we ever thought one would be able to take it …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a feature I totally love – a live heat map of what you are looking at … awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;www.attensee.com&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-381&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2015/02/Screen-Shot-2015-02-07-at-23.11.47-300x200.png&#34; alt=&#34;Screen Shot 2015-02-07 at 23.11.47&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;200&#34; srcset=&#34;2015/02/Screen-Shot-2015-02-07-at-23.11.47-300x200.png 300w, 2015/02/Screen-Shot-2015-02-07-at-23.11.47-749x500.png 749w, 2015/02/Screen-Shot-2015-02-07-at-23.11.47-500x334.png 500w, 2015/02/Screen-Shot-2015-02-07-at-23.11.47.png 1008w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dplyr is growing up &amp;#8230;</title>
      <link>/post/2014-09-25-dplyr-is-growing-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2014 01:37:27 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2014-09-25-dplyr-is-growing-up/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/uploads//2014/09/tvs-old-new.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-361&#34; src=&#34;/uploads//2014/09/tvs-old-new-300x170.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;tvs-old+new&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;170&#34; srcset=&#34;2014/09/tvs-old-new-300x170.jpg 300w, 2014/09/tvs-old-new.jpg 400w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;dplyr is the new plyr – and it is awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;fast, consistent and easy to read … check out a set of instructional pages, presentation and videos 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.r-bloggers.com/hands-on-dplyr-tutorial-for-faster-data-manipulation-in-r/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://had.co.nz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hadley Wickham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Die Zeit Wissen &amp;#8230; schreibt über Essensentscheidungen</title>
      <link>/post/2014-08-22-die-zeit-wissen-schreibt-uber-essensentscheidungen/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2014 14:26:12 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2014-08-22-die-zeit-wissen-schreibt-uber-essensentscheidungen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mal was Längeres zu unseren Lieblingsthemen: Essen und Entscheidungsforschung … Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/uploads//2014/08/2014-08-19_DieZeitWissen-wie-sie-beim-essen-die-richtigen-entscheidungen-treffen.pdf&#34;&gt;2014-08-19_DieZeitWissen-wie-sie-beim-essen-die-richtigen-entscheidungen-treffen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When something old &amp;#8230;</title>
      <link>/post/2014-05-07-when-something-old/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2014 01:12:06 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2014-05-07-when-something-old/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;p1&#34;&gt;
  Schulte-Mecklenbeck, M., &amp; Kühberger, A. (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;/uploads//2014/05/Schulte-Mecklenbeck2014.pdf&#34;&gt;Out of sight – out of mind? Information acquisition patterns in risky choice framing&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Polish Psychological Bulletin&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;45&lt;/i&gt;, 21–28.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p1&#34;&gt;
  I teamed up with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uni-salzburg.at/index.php?id=29678&#34;&gt;Anton Kühberger&lt;/a&gt; to write about one of our old, favorite topics: framing and process tracing &amp;#8230;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p1&#34;&gt;
  Here is the abstract:&lt;br /&gt; We investigate whether risky choice framing, i.e., the preference of a sure over an equivalent risky option when choosing among gains, and the reverse when choosing among losses, depends on redundancy and density of information available in a task. Redundancy, the saliency of missing information, and density, the description of options in one or multiple chunks, was manipulated in a matrix setup presented in MouselabWeb. On the choice level we found a framing effect only in setups with non-redundant information. On the process level outcomes attracted more acquisitions than probabilities, irrespective of redundancy. A dissociation between acquisition behavior and choice calls for a critical discussion of the limits of process-tracing measures for understanding and predicting choices in decision making tasks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p1&#34;&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper on food choice and simple heuristics</title>
      <link>/post/2013-08-16-new-paper-on-food-choice-and-simple-heuristics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2013 06:57:52 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2013-08-16-new-paper-on-food-choice-and-simple-heuristics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We got a new paper out on how people (consumers) use simple rules to make food choices. This is work in collaboration with the Nestlé Research Center in Lausanne.&lt;br&gt;
Here is the reference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p1&#34;&gt;
  Schulte-Mecklenbeck, M., Sohn, M., Bellis, E., Martin, N., &amp; Hertwig, R. (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.schulte-mecklenbeck.com/pubs/Schulte2013.pdf&#34;&gt;A Lack of Appetite for Information and Computation: Simple Heuristics in Food Choice&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Appetite&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;71&lt;/i&gt;, 242–251.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The predominant, but largely untested, assumption in research on food choice is that people obey the classic commandments of rational behavior: they carefully look up every piece of relevant information, weight each piece according to subjective importance, and then combine them into a judgment or choice. In real world situations, however, the available time, motivation, and computational resources may simply not suffice to keep these commandments. Indeed, there is a large body of research suggesting that human choice is often better accommodated by heuristics—simple rules that enable decision making on the basis of a few, but important, pieces of information. We investigated the prevalence of such heuristics in a computerized experiment that engaged participants in a series of choices between two lunch dishes. Employing MouselabWeb, a process-tracing technique, we found that simple heuristics described an overwhelmingly large proportion of choices, whereas strategies traditionally deemed rational were barely apparent in our data. Replicating previous findings, we also observed that visual stimulus segments received a much larger proportion of attention than any nutritional values did. Our results suggest that, consistent with human behavior in other domains, people make their food choices on the basis of simple and informationally frugal heuristics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limesurvey randomizing</title>
      <link>/post/2013-06-03-limesurvey-randomizing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2013 12:55:47 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2013-06-03-limesurvey-randomizing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is kind of an odd problem.&lt;br&gt;
For the following pretty straight forward question: How do I randomise questions within a group in 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.limesurvey.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Limesurvey&lt;/a&gt;? It seems to be really hard to find an answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the help of Jonas I figured out that there is a randomisation option hidden in the ‘Advanced Settings’ section of a question. What you have to do is provide the same number (this is important) for each question in a group that you want to randomise. Limesurvey will then take care of the rest. It did not seem to work if I named the variable with a string, eg, ‘group1’ but only numeric counters work fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks Jonas! (I would not have finished at all) …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;2013/06/Screen-Shot-2013-06-03-at-9.37.52-PM1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-269&#34; src=&#34;2013/06/Screen-Shot-2013-06-03-at-9.37.52-PM1-300x101.png&#34; alt=&#34;Screen Shot 2013-06-03 at 9.37.52 PM&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;101&#34; srcset=&#34;2013/06/Screen-Shot-2013-06-03-at-9.37.52-PM1-300x101.png 300w, 2013/06/Screen-Shot-2013-06-03-at-9.37.52-PM1-500x169.png 500w, 2013/06/Screen-Shot-2013-06-03-at-9.37.52-PM1.png 624w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>*apply in all its variations &amp;#8230;</title>
      <link>/post/2012-10-13-apply-in-all-its-variations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2012 11:05:38 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2012-10-13-apply-in-all-its-variations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/3505701/r-grouping-functions-sapply-vs-lapply-vs-apply-vs-tapply-vs-by-vs-aggrega/7141669#7141669&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is an excellent 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt; post on how *apply in all its variations can be used.&lt;br&gt;
One of the followups points at 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://plyr.had.co.nz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;plyr&lt;/a&gt; (from demi-R-god 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://had.co.nz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hadley Wickham&lt;/a&gt;) which provides a consistent naming convention for all the *apply variations. I like plyr a lot, because like ggplot, it is easy to grasp and relatively intuitive to find an answer to even tricky problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the translation from *apply to plyr …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Base function   Input   Output   plyr function 
---------------------------------------
aggregate        d       d       ddply + colwise 
apply            a       a/l     aaply / alply 
by               d       l       dlply 
lapply           l       l       llply  
mapply           a       a/l     maply / mlply 
replicate        r       a/l     raply / rlply 
sapply           l       a       laply 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Style Guide</title>
      <link>/post/2012-09-21-r-style-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2012 22:59:18 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2012-09-21-r-style-guide/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is mainly a note to self:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several style guides for R out there. I particularly like the one from 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://google.github.io/styleguide/Rguide.xml&#34; title=&#34;Google R Style Guide&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt; and the somewhat lighter 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://stat405.had.co.nz/r-style.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;version of Hadley&lt;/a&gt; (ggplot god).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of that style guide thinking started after a question on &amp;lt;stackoverflow.com&amp;gt; about R workflow … How do we organize large R projects. Hadley (again) is favoring an Load-Clean-Func-Do approach which looks somewhat like that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;load.R # load data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;clean.R # clean up crap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;func.R # add functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do.R # do the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kind of started doing something along these lines, with splitting files into load/clean (still together, could go separate …), cleaning, graphing (which does not make a lot of sense in an extra file) and large junks of analysis … got to redo some directories now …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other cool links from today’s follow-this-link trip: 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.getskeleton.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.getskeleton.com/&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://subtlepatterns.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://subtlepatterns.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Religion and # of babies &amp;#8230;</title>
      <link>/post/2012-05-24-religion-and-of-babies/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2012 00:05:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2012-05-24-religion-and-of-babies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Religion seems to have little influence on the # of babies per woman – who might have thought …&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/hans_rosling_religions_and_babies.html?utm_source=newsletter_weekly_2012-05-22&amp;amp;utm_campaign=newsletter_weekly&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is another excellent talk of Hans Rösling on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On writing in social science</title>
      <link>/post/2012-02-03-on-writing-in-social-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2012 02:37:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2012-02-03-on-writing-in-social-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gladwell.com/bio.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Malcom Gladwell&lt;/a&gt; (author of 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.de/Blink-Power-Thinking-Without/dp/0141022043/ref=sr_1_1?s=books-intl-de&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1328261480&amp;amp;sr=1-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Blink&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.de/Tipping-Point-Little-Things-Difference/dp/0316679070/ref=sr_1_1?s=books-intl-de&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1328261757&amp;amp;sr=1-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tipping point&lt;/a&gt;) meets 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://danariely.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dan Ariely&lt;/a&gt; (author of 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.de/Predictably-Irrational-Hidden-Forces-Decisions/dp/0007256531/ref=sr_1_1?s=books-intl-de&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1328261784&amp;amp;sr=1-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Predictively Irrational&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://improbable.com/ig/winners/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ig Nobel Prize Winner&lt;/a&gt;) to chat on what are good strategies in selecting topics to write about and the difficulties of wading through complex information … Its called a 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://journalistsresource.org/reference/research/research-chat-dan-ariely-malcolm-gladwell-social-science/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;research chat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>how decisions deplete and breaks help</title>
      <link>/post/2011-08-18-how-decisions-deplete-and-breaks-help/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2011 22:31:18 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2011-08-18-how-decisions-deplete-and-breaks-help/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The New York Times published a 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://nyti.ms/qpAHLe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;nice overview&lt;/a&gt; of the work on decision making and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ego_depletion&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ego depletion&lt;/a&gt; (often ego depletion is used as a synonym with resource depletion, which is somewhat confusing because of the use of the later in economy to described the situation when raw materials are exhausted in a region).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new paper from 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://gsbapps.stanford.edu/facultyprofiles/biomain.asp?id=87752309&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jonathan Levav&lt;/a&gt; (now at Standford – congrats!) is prominently featured in the above article. 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/108/17/6889.full.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Levav et al&lt;/a&gt; analysed rulings in court cases and link them to the time when these rulings were made during the day. They showed that after breaks (lunches) the probability of getting probation dramatically increased, a results that blends nicely into the ego depletion idea which states that self-control is a limited resource that is depleted by decision (rulings) and can be restored by, e.g., rest.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why anybody should learn/use R &amp;#8230;</title>
      <link>/post/2011-08-02-why-anybody-should-learnuse-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2011 06:36:14 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2011-08-02-why-anybody-should-learnuse-r/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had a discussion the other day on the re-appearing topic why one should learn R …&lt;br&gt;
I took the list below from the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.r-bloggers.com/10-reasons-why-a-grad-student-should-use-r/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R-Bloggers&lt;/a&gt; which argues why grad students should learn R:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R is free, and lets grad students escape the burdens of commercial license costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R has really good online documentation; and the community is unparalleled.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The command-line interface is perfect for learning by doing. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R is on the cutting edge, and expanding rapidly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The R programming language is intuitive.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R creates stunning visuals. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R and LaTeX work together — seamlessly. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R is used by practitioners in a plethora of academic disciplines. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R makes you think.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There’s always more than one way to accomplish something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a great list – I would add that from the perspective of an university it makes sense to save a lot of money in not having to buy licenses. And reproducability is great with R because the code is always written in a text-file and not bound by software versions (as in other three or four letter (feel free to combine from: [A, P, S]) packages).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>awesome visualization tool for R</title>
      <link>/post/2011-07-15-awesome-visualization-tool-for-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2011 04:07:04 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2011-07-15-awesome-visualization-tool-for-r/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/googleVis/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/googleVis/&lt;/a&gt; enables chart generation similar to the ones instroduced by 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Rosling&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hans Roesling&lt;/a&gt; in his 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Rosling&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TED talk&lt;/a&gt; on poverty – extremly cool 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>resinstalling packages in R after update</title>
      <link>/post/2011-04-14-resinstalling-packages-in-r-after-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 23:15:45 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2011-04-14-resinstalling-packages-in-r-after-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is old - by should still work :) - comment on how to do this in 2019 below &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new version 2.13.0 of 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.r-project.org/&#34; title=&#34;R&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; has just been released and with the update comes the pain of re-installing all the packages from the old installation on the new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/&#34; title=&#34;Stackoverflow&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt; to the rescue! This 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1401904/painless-way-to-install-a-new-version-of-r&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;posting&lt;/a&gt; provides a simple two step process of first writing a list of packages into a file on the disk in the old version, installing the new version and then comparing the exported list to the currently installed packages in the new version with setdiff. I just went through the process and have to say that it is deadeasy! Below the code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;run in the old version of R&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;packages &amp;lt;- installed.packages()[,&amp;quot;Package&amp;quot;] 
save(packages, file=&amp;quot;Rpackages&amp;quot;) `
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install new R version&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;run in the new version&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;load(&amp;quot;Rpackages&amp;quot;)
for (p in setdiff(packages, installed.packages()[,&amp;quot;Package&amp;quot;]))
install.packages(p)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day this is outdated - with the new RStudio version you can simply add your packages with &lt;code&gt;library()&lt;/code&gt; and then simply click on &lt;code&gt;install packages&lt;/code&gt; in the RStudio interface.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sustainable research</title>
      <link>/post/2011-04-10-sustainable-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2011 04:25:33 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2011-04-10-sustainable-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A sister blog with interesting contributions on what open source software researcher can use to work sustainable …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;a title=&#34;Sustainable Research&#34; href=&#34;http://www.surefoss.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.surefoss.org/&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Psychology as a reproducible Science</title>
      <link>/post/2011-03-15-psychology-as-a-reproducible-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 13:30:49 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2011-03-15-psychology-as-a-reproducible-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is Psychology ready for reproducible research?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today the typical research process in psychology looks generally like this: we collect data; analyze them in many ways; write a draft article based on some of the results; submit the draft to a journal; maybe produce a revision following the suggestions of the reviewers and editors; and hopefully live long enough to actually see it published. All of these steps are closed to the public except for the last one – the publication of the (often substantially) revised version of the paper. Journal editors and reviewers evaluate the written work submitted to them, they trust that the analyses described in the submission are done in a principled and correct way. Editors and reviewers are the only external part of this process who will have an active influence on what analyses are done. After the publication of an article the public has the opportunity to write comments or ask the authors for the actual datasets for re-analysis. Often however, getting access to data from published papers is hard, if not often impossible (Savage &amp;amp; Vickers, 2009; Wicherts, Borsboom, Kats, &amp;amp; Molenaar, 2006).  Unfortunately only the gist of the analyses are described in the paper and neither exact verification nor innovative additional analyses are possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What could be a solution for this problem? An example from computer science provides a concept called “literate programming” which was advocated by one of the field’s grandmasters, Donald Knuth, in 1984. Knuth suggested that documentation (comments in the code) should be just as important as the actual code itself. This idea was reflected nearly 20 years later when Schwab et al. (2000) formulated a concept that “replication by other scientists” is a central aim and guardian for intellectual quality; they coined the term “reproducible research” for such a process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s move the research process to a more open, reproducible structure, in which scientific peers have the ability to evaluate not only the final publication but also the data and the analyses.&lt;br&gt;
Ideally, research papers would have code for analyses which are commented in detail and are submitted in tandem with drafts as well as the original datasets. Anybody, not only a restricted group of select reviewers and editors, could reproduce all the steps of the analysis and follow the logic of arguments on not only the conceptual level but at an analytic level as well. This openness facilities easy reanalysis of data also. Meta-analysis could be done more frequently and with greater resolution as the actual data are available. Moreover, this configuration would allow us collectively to estimate effects in the population and not restrict our attention to independent small samples (see Henrich, Heine, &amp;amp; Norenzayan, 2010 for a discussion of this topic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do we need to achieve this? From a policy perspective, journals would have to add the requirement for data and code submission together with the draft of each empirical paper. Some journals already provide the option to do that (e.g., Behavior Research Methods) in the supplemental material section on a voluntary base, some require the submission of all necessary material to replicate the reported results (e.g., Econometrica), however most do not offer such a possibility (it is of course possible to provide such materials through private or university web sites, but this is a haphazard and decentralized arrangement).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools are a second important part of facilitating this openness. Three open source (free of cost) components could provide the bases for reproducible research:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R (R Development Core Team, 2010) is widely recognized (cite) as the “language of statistics” and builds on writing code instead of a “click and forget” type of analysis that other software packages encourage. R is open source, comes with a large number of extensions for advanced statistical analysis and can be run on any computer platform, including as a Web based application (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.R-project.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.R-project.org&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LaTeX was invented to provide a tool for anybody to produce high quality publications independent of the computer system used (i.e. one could expect the same results everywhere, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.latex-project.org/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.latex-project.org/)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweave (Leisch, 2002) connects R and LaTeX providing the opportunity to write a research paper and do the data analysis in parallel, in a well documented and reproducible way (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.uni-muenchen.de/~leisch/Sweave/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.stat.uni-muenchen.de/~leisch/Sweave/)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power of these different tools comes from the combination of their being open source, their widespread adoption (across a wide range of fields in sciences), and the fully transparent means by which data analysis is conducted and reported.  It levels the playing field and means that anybody with an Internet connection and a computer can take part in evolving scientific progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Godfrey Saxe famously said that: “Laws, like sausages, cease to inspire respect in proportion as we know how they are made.” We should strive that this is not true for psychology as a science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog-attack</title>
      <link>/post/2011-03-01-blog-attack/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 01:58:43 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2011-03-01-blog-attack/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~cook/movabletype/archives/2011/02/behavioral_econ.html?utm_source=feedburner&amp;amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A&amp;#43;StatisticalModelingCausalInferenceAndSocialScience&amp;#43;%28Statistical&amp;#43;Modeling%2C&amp;#43;Causal&amp;#43;Inference%2C&amp;#43;and&amp;#43;Social&amp;#43;Science%29&amp;amp;utm_content=Google&amp;#43;Reader&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is what 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Andrew Gelman&lt;/a&gt; writes about an 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spousonomics.com/1821/2011/02/economists-in-love-colin-camerer/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hss.caltech.edu/~camerer/camerer.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Colin Camerer&lt;/a&gt; gave on 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spousonomics.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Spousomonics&lt;/a&gt; … Looking forward to Camerer’s reply …&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where you end up, having a PhD</title>
      <link>/post/2010-08-18-where-you-end-up-having-a-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Aug 2010 06:20:29 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2010-08-18-where-you-end-up-having-a-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The illustrated guide from Kindergarten to PhD …&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;http://matt.might.net/articles/phd-school-in-pictures/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://matt.might.net/articles/phd-school-in-pictures/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>two good things come together</title>
      <link>/post/2010-07-15-two-good-things-come-together/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2010 01:49:54 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2010-07-15-two-good-things-come-together/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.latexlab.org/docs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://docs.latexlab.org/docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
LaTeX and Google Docs together in one nice (free)application – this is a brilliant idea, which gives you the power of LaTeX combined with the excellent collaboration possiblities of Google Docs – if I would have a button it would say “I like” …&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R and the World Cup</title>
      <link>/post/2010-07-13-r-and-the-world-cup/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2010 00:48:38 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2010-07-13-r-and-the-world-cup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Across the street at the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.revolutionanalytics.com/2010/07/charting-the-world-cup.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Revolution blog&lt;/a&gt; a nice example of using R with data from the cloud (see another post on this topic 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.schulte-mecklenbeck.com/?p=105&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) shows us the distribution of fouls during the just finished World Cup in a nice barchart. Even more interesting than the fact that Holland rules this category is the way the data are collected from a Google spreadsheet page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the following simple code line:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;teams &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;http://spreadsheets.google.com/pub?key=tOM2qREmPUbv76waumrEEYg&amp;amp;#038;single=true&amp;amp;#038;gid=0&amp;amp;#038;range=A1%3AAG15&amp;amp;#038;output=csv&amp;quot;) &lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
We can read a specific part from a spreadsheet hosted on Google into our local R environment. Some deatils: &amp;ldquo;&amp;amp;gid=&amp;rdquo; (sheet number) and &amp;ldquo;%range=&amp;rdquo; (cell ranges: A1%3A ) and &amp;ldquo;&amp;amp;output=csv&amp;rdquo; to download in CSV format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some more lines, using the awsome 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://had.co.nz/ggplot2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; library(qqplot2)&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; FOULS=t(DF2)[,c(&#39;Fouls&#39;)]&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; qplot(names(FOULS), as.numeric(FOULS), geom=&amp;quot;bar&amp;quot;, stat=&#39;identity&#39;, fill=Fouls) + xlab(&#39;Country&#39;) + ylab(&#39;Fouls&#39;) + coord_flip() + scale_fill_continuous(low=&amp;quot;black&amp;quot;, high=&amp;quot;red&amp;quot;) + labs(fill=&#39;Fouls&#39;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can produce the following chart:&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;2010/07/World_Cup_2010_Fouls.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;2010/07/World_Cup_2010_Fouls-300x300.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;World_Cup_2010_Fouls&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-121&#34; srcset=&#34;2010/07/World_Cup_2010_Fouls-300x300.png 300w, 2010/07/World_Cup_2010_Fouls-150x150.png 150w, 2010/07/World_Cup_2010_Fouls.png 400w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two things to note:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;c(&#39;Fouls&#39;)&lt;/code&gt; is a handy way to address columns in a R data frame by name&lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;scale_fill_continuous(low=&amp;quot;black&amp;quot;, high=&amp;quot;red&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt; takes care of the color coding of the bars in reference to the number of fouls&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easy and straight forward - ah - great job Spain 🙂 !!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R goes cloud</title>
      <link>/post/2010-04-16-r-goes-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2010 23:24:03 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2010-04-16-r-goes-cloud/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.ucla.edu/~jeroen/cv.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jeroen Ooms&lt;/a&gt; did for R what Google did for editing documents online. He created several software packages that help running R with a nice frontend over the Internet.&lt;br&gt;
I first learned about Jeroen’s website through his 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.ucla.edu/~jeroen/ggplot2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;implementation of ggplot2&lt;/a&gt; – this page is useful to generate graphs with the powerful ggplot2 package without R knowledge, however it is even more helpful to learn ggplot2 code with the View-code panel function which displays the underlying R code. If you are into random effect models another package connected to 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.ucla.edu/~jeroen/lme4.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;lme4&lt;/a&gt; will guide you step by step through model building.&lt;br&gt;
I think this is a great step forward for R and cloud computing!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LaTeX looks more scientific</title>
      <link>/post/2010-03-18-latex-looks-more-scientific/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2010 06:42:04 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2010-03-18-latex-looks-more-scientific/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are long discussions on the benefits of LaTeX over Word, but this statement from a (not too serious) 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/unpublished/zombies.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; of 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Andrew Gelman&lt;/a&gt; (a Professor of Statistics and Political Sciences at Columbia University) hits the spot: 
&lt;a href=&#34;2010/03/Screen-shot-2010-03-18-at-2.29.06-PM1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;2010/03/Screen-shot-2010-03-18-at-2.29.06-PM1-300x56.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Screen shot 2010-03-18 at 2.29.06 PM&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;56&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-99&#34; srcset=&#34;2010/03/Screen-shot-2010-03-18-at-2.29.06-PM1-300x56.png 300w, 2010/03/Screen-shot-2010-03-18-at-2.29.06-PM1.png 674w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accepting to fail (in the name of science)</title>
      <link>/post/2009-12-22-accepting-to-fail-in-the-name-of-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2009 05:00:24 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2009-12-22-accepting-to-fail-in-the-name-of-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Very interesting 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com/magazine/2009/12/fail_accept_defeat/all/1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;article in WIRED&lt;/a&gt; on accepting failure and how ignoring it changes the way scientists make progress (or not).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good theme for new years resolutions …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime: Happy Holidays!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How WEIRD subjects can be overcome &amp;#8230; a comment on Henrich et al.</title>
      <link>/post/2009-12-12-how-weird-subjects-can-be-overcome-a-comment-on-henrich-et-al/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2009 06:11:14 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2009-12-12-how-weird-subjects-can-be-overcome-a-comment-on-henrich-et-al/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Joe 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psych.ubc.ca/~henrich/home.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Henrich&lt;/a&gt; published a target article in BBS talking about how economics and psychology base their research on WEIRD (Western, Educated, Industrialized, Rich and Democratic) subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the whole abstract:&lt;br&gt;
—&lt;br&gt;
Behavioral scientists routinely publish broad claims about human psychology and behavior in the world’s top journals based on samples drawn entirely from Western, Educated, Industrialized, Rich and Democratic (WEIRD) societies. Researchers—often implicitly—assume that either there is little variation across human populations, or that these “standard subjects” are as representative of the species as any other population. Are these assumptions justified? Here, our review of the comparative database from across the behavioral sciences suggests both that there is substantial variability in experimental results across populations and that WEIRD subjects are particularly unusual compared with the rest of the species—frequent outliers. The domains reviewed include visual perception, fairness, cooperation, spatial reasoning, categorization and inferential induction, moral reasoning, reasoning styles, self-concepts and related motivations, and the heritability of IQ. The findings suggest that members of WEIRD societies, including young children, are among the least representative populations one could find for generalizing about humans. Many of these findings involve domains that are associated with fundamental aspects of psychology, motivation, and behavior—hence, there are no obvious a priori grounds for claiming that a particular behavioral phenomenon is universal based on sampling from a single subpopulation. Overall, these empirical patterns suggests that we need to be less cavalier in addressing questions of human nature on the basis of data drawn from this particularly thin, and rather unusual, slice of humanity. We close by proposing ways to structurally re-organize the behavioral sciences to best tackle these challenges.&lt;br&gt;
—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to make three suggestions that could help to overcome the era of WEIRD subjects and generate more reliable and representative data. These suggestions will mainly touch contrasts 2, 3 and 4 elaborated by Henrich, Heine and Norezayan. While my suggestions tackle these contrasts from a technical and experimental perspective they do not provide a general solution for the first contrast on industrialized versus small scale societies. Here are my suggestions: 1) replications in multiple labs, 2) internet based experimentation and 3) drawing representative samples from a population.&lt;br&gt;
The first suggestion, replication in multiple labs, foremost touches aspects like replication, multiple populations and open data access. For a publication in a journal a replication of an experiment in a different lab would be obligatory. The replication would then be published with the original, e.g., in the form of a comment. This would ensure that other research labs in other states or countries are involved and very different parts of the population could be sampled. Also results of experiments would be freely available to the public and the data sharing problem in Psychology, as described in the target article, but also in other fields like Medicine (Savage &amp;amp; Vieckers, 2009) would be a problem of the past. Of course such a step would be closely linked with certain standards on the one hand in building experiments and on the other hand in storing data. While a standard way to build experiments seems unlikely there are many methods available in computer science to store data in a reusable, for example through the usage of XML (Extensible Markup Language).&lt;br&gt;
The second suggestion is based on the drawing of representative samples from the population. As described in the target article, research often suffers from a restriction to extreme subgroups from the population, from which generalized results are drawn. However, there is published work that overcomes these restrictions. As an example I would like to use the Hertwig, Zangerl, Biedert and Margraf (2008) paper on probabilistic numeracy. The authors based their study on a random-quote sample from the Swiss population including indicators as language, area where participant is living, gender and age. To fulfill all the necessary criteria 1000 participants were recruited using telephone interviews. Such studies are certainly more expensive and somewhat restricted to simpler experimental setups (Hertwig et al., used telephone interviews based on questionnaires).&lt;br&gt;
The third suggestion adds additional data collection in a second location: the Internet. The emphasis in the last sentence should be set on ‘add’. Data collection solely Internet based is of course possible, already often performed and published in high impact journals. Online experimentation is technically much less demanding than ten years ago due to the availability of ready made solutions for questionnaires or even experiments. The point I would like to make here should not be built on a separation of lab and online based experiments. My suggestion combines these two research locations and enables a researcher to profit from the many benefits arising. A possible scenario could include running an experiment in the laboratory first to guarantee, among other things, high control on the situation in order to show an effect with a small, restricted sample. In a second step the experiment is transferred to the Web and run online, admittedly giving away some of the control but providing the large benefit of having access to a diverse, large samples of participants from different populations easily. As an example I would like to point to a recent blog and related experiments started by Paolacci and Warglien (2009) at the University of Venice, Italy. These researchers started replicating well known experiments from the decision making literature like framing, anchoring or the conjunction fallacy with a service called the Mechanical Turk provided by Amazon. This service is based on the idea of crowdsourcing (outsourcing a task to a large group of people) and lets a researcher have easy access to a large group of motivated participants.&lt;br&gt;
Some final words on the combination and possible restrictions of the three suggestions. What would a combination of all three suggestions look like? It would be a replication of experiments, using representative samples of different populations in online experiments. This seems useful from a data quality, logistics and prize point of view. However, several issues were left untouched in my discussion, such as the question of independence of the second lab for replication studies, the restriction of representative samples to one country (as opposed to multiple comparisons as routinely found in, e.g., anthropological studies), the differences between online and lab based experimentation or the instances where equipment needed for an experiments (e.g., eye trackers or fMRI) does not allow for online experimentation. Keeping that in mind the above suggestions draw an idealized picture of how to run experiments and re-use the collected data, nevertheless I would argue that such steps could help to reduce the percentage of WEIRD subjects in research substantially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psycho.unibas.ch/index_html?content=person&amp;amp;detail=cv&amp;amp;abteilung=Angewandte&amp;amp;person=Hertwig&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hertwig&lt;/a&gt;, R., Zangerl, M.A., Biedert, E., &amp;amp; Margraf, J. (2008). The Public’s Probabilistic Numeracy: How Tasks, Education and Exposure to Games of Chance Shape It. Journal of Behavioral Decision Making, 21, 457-570.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paolacci, G., &amp;amp; Warglien, M. (2009). 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://experimentalturk.wordpress.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Experimental turk: A blog on social science experiments on Amazon Mechanical Turk&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed on November 17th 2009:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Savage, C.J., &amp;amp; Vickers, A.J. (2009). Empirical Study of Data Sharing by Authors Publishing in PLoS Journals. PLoS ONE 4(9): e7078.doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0007078&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lattice versus ggplot2</title>
      <link>/post/2009-10-24-lattice-versus-ggplot2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2009 20:15:50 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2009-10-24-lattice-versus-ggplot2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I really liked Lattice for generating graphs in R until I saw what ggplot2 can do …&lt;br&gt;
One of the big differences between the two is the theory on which ggplot2 is based upon. There are clear modular building blocks that can be applied in a consistent manner on any graph generated. Both packages are extremely versatile but at the end of the day I think ggplot2 provides a clearer structure and hence more flexibility …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://had.co.nz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hadley Wickham&lt;/a&gt; (the author of ggplot2) has a book out on 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0387981403?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hadlwick-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0387981403&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt; at Springer. Some sample chapters can be downloaded from his 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://had.co.nz/ggplot2/book/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;webpage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://learnr.wordpress.com/2009/06/28/ggplot2-version-of-figures-in-lattice-multivariate-data-visualization-with-r-part-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;learningR&lt;/a&gt; people have a long series of posts where they provide ggplot2 code for nearly all the graphs in the Lattice book … worth taking a look at!&lt;br&gt;
Here is an in depth&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R flashmob</title>
      <link>/post/2009-09-06-r-flashmob/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2009 23:07:06 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2009-09-06-r-flashmob/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From: The R Flashmob Project&lt;br&gt;
Subject: R Flashmob #2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are invited to take part in R Flashmob, the project that makes the&lt;br&gt;
world a better place by posting helpful questions and answers about the&lt;br&gt;
R statistical language to the programmer’s Q &amp;amp; A site stackoverflow.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please forward this to other people you know who might like to join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FAQ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q. Why would I want to join an inexplicable R mob?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. Tons of other people are doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q. Why else?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. Stackoverflow was built specifically for handling programming questions.&lt;br&gt;
It’s a better mousetrap. It offers search (and is well indexed by search engines),&lt;br&gt;
tagging, voting, the ability to choose the “best” answer to a question, and the ability to&lt;br&gt;
edit questions and answers as technology progresses. It has a karma system to&lt;br&gt;
reward people who are happy to help and discourage MLJs (mailing list jerks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q. Do the organizers of this MOB have any commercial interest in stackoverflow?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. None at all. We’re just convinced it is the best way to help and promote R. All&lt;br&gt;
the content submitted to stackoverflow is protected by a Creative Commons&lt;br&gt;
CC-Wiki License, meaning anyone is free to copy, distribute, transmit, and&lt;br&gt;
remix the information on stackoverflow. All the content on stackoverflow is&lt;br&gt;
regularly made available for download by the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;INSTRUCTIONS – R MOB #2&lt;br&gt;
Location: stackoverflow.com&lt;br&gt;
Start Date: Tuesday, September 8th, 2009&lt;br&gt;
Start Time:&lt;br&gt;
10:04 AM – US Pacific&lt;br&gt;
11:04 AM – US Mountain&lt;br&gt;
12:04 PM – US Central&lt;br&gt;
1:04 PM – US Eastern&lt;br&gt;
6:04 PM – UK&lt;br&gt;
7:04 PM – Continental W. Europe&lt;br&gt;
5:04 AM (Weds) – New Zealand (birthplace of R)&lt;br&gt;
Duration: 50 minutes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) At some point during the day on September 8th, synchronize your watch to&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;http://timeanddate.com/worldclock/personal.html?cities=137,75,64,179,136,37,22&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://timeanddate.com/worldclock/personal.html?cities=137,75,64,179,136,37,22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2) The mob should form at precisely 4 minutes past the hour and not beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(3) At 4 minutes past the hour, you should arrive at stackoverflow.com, log in,&lt;br&gt;
and post 3 R questions. Be sure to tag the questions “R”. See the posting&lt;br&gt;
guidelines at 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/faq&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://stackoverflow.com/faq&lt;/a&gt; to understand what makes a good&lt;br&gt;
question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(4) Follow R Flashmob updates at 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/rstatsmob&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://twitter.com/rstatsmob&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(5) Post twitter messages tagged #rstats and #rstatsmob during the mob,&lt;br&gt;
providing links to your questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(6) During the R MOB, you can chat with other participants on the #R channel&lt;br&gt;
on IRC (freenode). To do this, install the Chatzilla extension on Firefox.&lt;br&gt;
Click “freenode” on the main screen. Then type /join #R in the field at the&lt;br&gt;
bottom of the screen. Then chat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(7) If you finish posting your three questions within the 50 minutes, stick&lt;br&gt;
around to answer questions and give “up votes” to good questions and answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(8) IMPORTANT: After posting, sign the R Flashmob guestbook at&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/6F8B2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://bit.ly/6F8B2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(9) Return to what you would otherwise have been doing. Await&lt;br&gt;
instructions for R MOB #3.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flashlight paper draft</title>
      <link>/post/2009-07-13-flashlight-paper-draft/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2009 02:20:25 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2009-07-13-flashlight-paper-draft/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We submitted our Flashlight paper today. Find a draft at the address below:&lt;br&gt;
Schulte-Mecklenbeck, Michael , Murphy, Ryan O. and Hutzler, Florian,Flashlight – an Online Eye-Tracking Tool(July 13, 2009). Available at SSRN: 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://ssrn.com/abstract=1433225&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://ssrn.com/abstract=1433225&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The software will be uploaded to the project page 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://vlab.ethz.ch/vLab_Decision_Theory_and_Behavioral_Game_Theory/Flashlight.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://vlab.ethz.ch/vLab_Decision_Theory_and_Behavioral_Game_Theory/Flashlight.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have fun playing with it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LaTeX tips</title>
      <link>/post/2009-06-25-latex-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2009 11:13:33 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2009-06-25-latex-tips/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two things are often bothering when one starts to work with LaTeX: in text referencing of literature and Umlaute (for our German speaking friends) ****&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Referencing:&lt;/strong&gt; Here is a list of 5 types of in text referencing. To get them to work in a LaTeX file you need to define a referencing style in your document (in the example I use APA – American Psychological Association), you can of course use any style you want!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the header:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;usepackage{apacite}&lt;br&gt;
bibliographystyle{apacite}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the actual text part the command on the left results in the reference on the right:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cite{Bortz1993} – (Bortz, 1993)&lt;br&gt;
citeA{Bortz1993} – Bortz (1993)&lt;br&gt;
citeNP{Campbell1959} – Campbell, 1959&lt;br&gt;
citeauthor{Spiel2001} – Spiel citeyearNP{Bortz1993} – 1993&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the document enter a reference to your .bib file, in the example below my file is called biblio.bib: bibliography{biblio}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Umlaute&lt;/strong&gt;: In German there are several Umlaute that are not included in the standard english setup of a LaTeX installation. There are two ways to get them right: 1) given a standard LaTeX document use (again command on the left, result on the right): “a – ä “u – ü “o – ö) given that you actually want to write in German do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;usepackage[german]{babel}&lt;br&gt;
usepackage[ansinew]{inputenc}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two useful links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;1) Wikipedia book on LaTeX&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/LaTeX&#34;&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/LaTeX&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/LaTeX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;2) A &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uni-salzburg.at/portal/page?_pageid=138,456842&amp;_dad=portal&amp;_schema=PORTAL&#34;&gt;page&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Salzburg’s Psychology department (German!)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.users.sbg.ac.at/~gdkleiter/&#34;&gt;Gernot Kleiter&lt;/a&gt; was the person who introduced me to LaTeX, decision making, good experimenting … actually, there should be a whole post about him …&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>XAMPP activating mysql</title>
      <link>/post/2009-06-17-xampp-activating-mysql/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2009 12:50:56 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2009-06-17-xampp-activating-mysql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is the problem: I want to have a server (Apache, MySQL) on my local machine (for the current purpose it was a Windows machine) to do some developing, testing or a demo. Getting 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apachefriends.org/en/xampp.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;XAMPP&lt;/a&gt; at 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://sourceforge.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sourceforge&lt;/a&gt; is straight forward, installing it works like a charm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BUT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A problem coming back from time to time is the following: the MySQL daemon does not start.&lt;br&gt;
Hmmmm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some steps that helped me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make sure to deactivate any services related to MySQL and Apache&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shutdown XAMPP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to be sure I restart the machine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do not start XAMPP with the .bat file but use the MySQL and Apache batch scripts – these open a command window which you should not close as long as you use XAMPP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through these steps everything worked fine …&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>double, triple or even sextuple blind?</title>
      <link>/post/2009-06-14-double-triple-or-even-sextuple-blind/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2009 03:21:01 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2009-06-14-double-triple-or-even-sextuple-blind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is an interesting discussion on how the scientific review process should be handled going on at 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://orgtheory.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;orgtheory.net&lt;/a&gt; blog. The point is that the obvious shortcomings in the current review system (the authors know who the editor is (and vice versa), the reviewer knows (or can easily infer) who the author is …) can be handle through triple blind reviews: authors, reviewers AND editors are included (anonymous upload to a webpage (id through a code), quatruple blind reviews: no one know who the editor of the journal is, quintimple blind: after publication of a paper the authors name is kept secret for some years or, and that’s the actual kicker: sextuple blind: there is no journal name any more – just the paper and the users decide whether it is worth citing or not …&lt;br&gt;
In a more detailed way you can find this approach explained 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://orgtheory.wordpress.com/2007/01/23/a-modest-proposal-triple-blind-review/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inference and R</title>
      <link>/post/2009-06-05-inference-and-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2009 13:28:22 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2009-06-05-inference-and-r/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dan Goldstein posted a short 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.decisionsciencenews.com/?p=759&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;overview of Inference&lt;/a&gt; which allows working with R code in Microsoft Office and Excel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to point at 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.statistik.lmu.de/~leisch/Sweave/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sweave&lt;/a&gt; which does an excellent job in connecting R to LaTeX. Here is a short 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.umn.edu/~charlie/Sweave/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt; of Sweave which also connects the approach of Sweave to the ‘
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/lp.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;literate programming&lt;/a&gt;‘ idea of 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Donald Knuth&lt;/a&gt; (Father of ‘The Art of Computer Programming’ and TeX).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is to combine programming (an analysis in the case of R) with documentation into one process. This seems to be useful when one goes back to an older analysis and tries to find out what was done some months ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally you find a longer interview with Paul van Eikeren on the same topic 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.decisionstats.com/2009/06/04/interview-inference-for-r/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>create colored title in R plot</title>
      <link>/post/2009-05-17-create-colored-title-in-r-plot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2009 12:59:53 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2009-05-17-create-colored-title-in-r-plot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;David Smith has a very nice code example in which he sets the color of title word in a plot to the actual grouping color. Code can be found 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.revolution-computing.com/2009/01/multicolor-text-in-r.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This seems extremely useful for posters and presentations. I doubt however that journals would pick up on that …&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
